all right guys so we've learned a lot
about teaching bashes a first language
and I want to regroup and I want to just
review some things that we've covered so
far and I want to consider doing it a
different way so we're going to go
through the steps that we've gone
through so far but we're going to go
through them really quickly and we're
going to do them entirely differently um
I have been not confident
in uh how you guys are grasping the
difference between a function and sub
rtin and procedure and all that stuff
and quite honestly it's premature to
talk about that stuff when dealing with
bash um those concepts are coming from
what I used to teach which was python is
the first language and it's very easy to
do that that so I'm going to repeat for
the next 20 minutes or so I'm going to
repeat all the steps that I've done so
far with bash but we're going to do it
without blocks and we're going to do it
in a different way which I think will
help you understand it better the first
thing is we've already got our place to
save our stuff right we created
a single
program and in fact let's actually make
move this Let's Pretend We're going to
do it all over again even though you
know I'm going to hide it by making it
have a dot in front that's how you hide
things is you put a dot in front of it
okay so so here we go the first thing
we're going to do you don't know how to
do a thing um let's make a text file so
we're going to touch a text file we'll
call it hello and right now it's hello
right and you can actually run the
program by just running hello low
permission denied we can't so we need to
make it per so we can run it sood plus
xow do slash means in this directory
right here and you have to do that for
safety so now it's red uh and we see
that it's runnable and we do slow and we
can run it it doesn't do anything
there's no instructions in it but this
is the part where we get to talk about
bash is just a running interpreter it's
like you can put any instructions in
there that you can put here so let's
actually just say hello echo hello world
there's our first command and you can
see it Echo hello world let's put that
same command inside of that file so
we'll go into the file Echo hello
world okay same exact command now let's
run it dohow world and there you go it
runs it's the same as if we had typed it
that's we made our own command at that
point okay now I I went off I went down
a huge tangent when I first did this on
what if we tried to to do this
differently but that's all you really
need to know that's program that's
running that has instructions in it all
right so the next step is this let's put
some more instructions in it instead of
it having to say hello world what if we
what if we make it so that we wanted to
ask what our name was right well let's
make another program uh let's call
another program hi all right so uh copy
hello to hi and a lot of you are
watching this like oh my God he's doing
it all wrong I'm doing it from a very
basic level for someone who doesn't know
anything about coding so copy hello to
high let's make a new one all right so
let's change hi let's say we wanted to
ask a name so let's say instead of hello
world let's have it say hi Rob all right
so hi Rob or or whatever hi you you know
and so now we can run that Doh high and
we get high you now wouldn't it be great
if we could add it you know if you could
add a name to it right well how would we
do that right so let's actually go ahead
and set a variable so we're going to set
a variable we're going to say that my
name name equals and notice I'm doing it
on the shell okay so then we say name
equals
rub all right now we can change High to
use that variable we can change U to
name and now I can run it high and it
says oh it's blank what happened with
that
it doesn't know it does it it doesn't
know it why doesn't it know it the
reason it doesn't know name is because
it hasn't it doesn't know about it now I
could do this I could I could go into
the program and I could write name
equals Rob right and now I can do high
and it says High Rob because it knows
about it but how do I want that program
to know about the variable that I set so
like we get rid of this and it's still
go stop printing it out
so and that what that means is we need
to actually have a variable but instead
of having the variable be just visible
to this running program this running
process that we're in and we talked
about processes already we want it to be
visible to that process and every
process underneath it okay and it can
never be visible to stuff above that
that's insecure so what we do is we
export it so we're going to
export we're going to export that
variable and we we can do it by name
it's already been set we don't have to
do anything else now when we run/ High
it will work because we took that
variable and we changed its scope so by
default a variable in bash is only
visible to the running process right the
exact running process nothing under it
nothing above it by default but and a
variable is is kind of like a box that
you put stuff in as you saw you can put
whatever in there if I change it right
right I can say say name equals Doris
and I can say/ high and now it runs high
door right because it's a variable that
means it can change it varies it changes
um for the record by the way you can
make readon variables that don't ever
change but that's not important right
now so right now we just want that that
value to change there are all kinds of
environment variables that are already
on your computer and if you type EnV and
you can see them all right you can type
EnV pipe to more and you can see even
more of them right you can see all of
your environment variables doing
different things you have to type q but
these are all variables and they're in
all capitals and the reason they're in
all capitals is because they are
environment variables that are meant to
be used all over the place so this is a
convention from Unix and Bash that's
existed for a long time that means so
when they make a variable that is meant
to be used everywhere um that it's all
capitals to to Really you know clarify
this is meant to be used everywhere so
if I was going to make my name permanent
and make it so it could be used anywhere
I would put it you know I would put it
in my bash RC so let's actually do that
we're going to actually VI Etsy bashrc
or bash profile and we're going to go to
the end of it it doesn't matter what
yours says and then we're going to say
export name equals right
Rob so now if I every time I run my
program in order to get your bash shell
to reset you do exac bash
DL that we restart bash mine has a hard
long startup for lots of reasons but it
brings up a new one and now I can say
Echo uh name and it's there Doris is
there but it also has another one the
all caps one is Rob right so now we can
change High to be all Cap's name and
that kind of signals that I'm expecting
this to come from everything now there's
no requirement for to be all capitals
and there are a lot of people that use
all capitals for local variables that
never leave the file I think that's a
bad idea I think the idea of all cap
variables is very precise it's it means
that this came from outside of this
program and I don't think that you
should set your variable names to be all
uppercase in a local uh file I think
it's a bad practice uh a lot of people
do that but I think it's a really bad
idea the only thing that belongs in all
capitals is something that's getting
reused between multiple commands right
and so actually how would we do that we
could actually make hello use the same
thing hello world and we could say hello
name here and obviously you see what
it's doing there right okay next so so
far we've covered all the basics about
how to make different programs and how
to set variables and how those things
can change here's something cool you can
actually change the environment variable
temporarily for a program right so I can
do this I can do name equal Doris and
then I can do/ high and that will change
the variable just for that execution of
the program a lot of people don't know
that a lot of people don't know that you
can do that um so by doing that then
what we do is we haven't changed the
name in the overall that only changed it
for that one process that was running so
like if i e if I do Echo name here you
can see that it's still Rob okay so this
is actually a really common thing uh
there are a lot lot of programs that do
this um for example the go programming
language actually sets the the operating
system uh this way when you're doing a
go build and you can build uh your
binaries for a different operating
system than the one you're building on
it's called cross compilation it's
really cool and this is a way of
changing the environments and setting
those variables those environment
variables for that program that's
running on that line only okay even
though it has been exported it's it's
you get your old writing it for that one
moment okay so so now we've covered
we've got hello here and we've got hi
and you can see that it's just one
command and it's in there let's actually
expand on that so but before we get too
much further along uh you may have
notice that when you open up your
program you don't get any fancy syntax
highlighting or anything and the reason
for that is because the program the the
computer that your editor it do no idea
what type of programming language that
is and I'm going to show you a couple
things that people do to get around that
the first thing they do I detest it's
absolutely a horrible idea and I'm going
to tell you why right now but what they
do is they'll they'll make the name of
the program
hello.sh all right and now you have a
hello now when I go to edit my hello.sh
it'll know what kind of thing it is
because it has an extension but it's a
bad idea and let me tell you why what
happens if I want to change this
language to Pearl right so let's
actually do that and and I'm only going
to do this to show you or python I'm
going to use Pearl because I like it but
if you want to use python or Ruby or any
other interpreter language view my
guests but I'm going to make a point
here so the first time I change the
language right I'm going to change the
language to be pearl print hello
name first of all you can't you know
there's lots of things you can't do you
got to have quotes around a thing uh in
Pro you got to have I mean this is why
people don't like it but you can it's
got to have a semicolon all right that's
a string in a carriage a line uh a form
feed or a line return uh I mean um uh
what am I saying it's a ah not a form Fe
what am I saying it's a it's not a
carriage return it's a line line
thing it's not a line return either it's
there's Carri Line Feed Line Feed that's
it never mind so yeah and these relate
to teletype machines Line Feed yeah I
just conally spaced so so now what so
now when I run it is it going to work no
why isn't it going to work because it's
still trying to run it as bash it's
using the command line interpreter that
we're using right now that we're ex
we're interacting with every every
Command right and so when we put those
commands from the command line we put
them into a file that's all well and
good as long as the file is still bash
but in this case it's not it's a
different thing so we need to give a
hint to The Bash interpreter to say hey
no don't use yourself here we want you
to go use another program and so this is
where shebang comes in and we're going
to change change this to hello we're
going to put a shebang in so the bash
interpreter and pretty much any language
shell command line interpreter will look
at the first two characters of the file
and if it's a shebang line it will use
whatever's on that line to run the
program so in this case we're going to
say user bin Pearl all right and uh
shell check only supports oh this is
interesting look uh scripts it doesn't
support
Pearl why is C Che freaking out
do you know why I bet you can guess I
bet you can
guess why is shell Che freaking out do
you see down
here
Oops why why down here yeah look down
here look at look at what look down in
the corner down here what kind of
program does it think it is it thinks
it's shill why why does it think it's
shell
do you know why I hate suffixes now no
it's modded it's
executable that's why I hate suffixes I
was not allowed to change the language
of the program because of the
suffix if I wanted to do this I'd have
to do
this which a lot of people do and I hate
because now you know who cares what the
language is that's completely non-unix
that's a completely non-un way to do
things my friends let me just I I I this
is one of my biggest pet peeves of all
people who use suffixes unnecessarily
because you are permanently forcing
dependencies on a specific
implementation of the language so that
command can no longer be Rewritten in go
see rust or anything and everything that
you have that depends on that program
has now got a hardcoded broken
dependency on a specific
shell you know do you have any idea go
on GitHub and look at all the people
that do this okay I'm going to calm down
now but I'm telling you don't do that
and you know why now you just saw why
the thing you should have done instead
is just kept the name to be hello and
then it's perfectly happy to change the
language who cares you want to rewrite
it in Ruby be my guest it'll be the same
thing you want to compile it as go let's
do that all right let's move hello to
hello you know old let's write a quick
go program all right so let's write VI
hello I'm just just as point of
illustration all right so go there's
there it is we say change this change
this to hello all right now we're going
to compile It Go builds uh hello uh.
go uh and we build that right here and
now we have a Hello program now look at
this file hello
all right it's now an executable arm
program exact same command does the same
thing but this is now a
binary I rest my case okay if if I if if
if you continue to put suffixes on your
files that's on you because now you know
why it's a stupid ass idea all right I'm
moving on I am so tired of that okay so
move hello let's get rid of hello
go uh move hello D old to
hello and you can do what you want but
that includes being you know so anyway
VI
hello and here we go so so we're back to
Pearl and it's like I don't know what
you want to do here it's like what are
you even trying to do use once possible
typo uh main name use only
once what's going on
here shell Che can't speak
Pearl wait a
second wait a
second does Shell Che no
pearl
no huh oh that's coming from Pearl
critique never mind yeah this is if if
you're going to do PE I have my shell
format over this too uh only use once
possible typo oh right right right oh
that's not a that's not a thing in in in
U
uh in U in Pro you have to do
this just in case you guys are
wondering yeah I know this is not about
Pearl but that's that's that's what's
got happen
there all right same same idea though so
this idea about about using environment
variables that every single language
uses that okay on every single operating
system so knowing about those variables
uh you know that already exists on the
system yes you can code them in your
programs and we're going to do that next
but what I wanted to show you is you can
set those variables right away
interactively all right so let's pick up
where we left off um H we we we've done
our hello program hello we we made it
into
Pearl um let's uh let's actually change
back to bash so but I'm going to do one
other thing we going to do user B EMV
bash which I is insecure but if you're
just doing it for yourself it's okay
this will prevent you from having to
change this line on every single
computer you might ever want to run this
on um you know I could do this I could
say um so you can do this too which bash
and bang bang two exclamation points and
run that through bash and that will give
you the exact path to bash let's talk
about that so that is where bash lives
so we need to have a conversation now
and we have to talk about pathing and I
know this is normally pre premature in a
programming sort of conversation but
it's really important that we talk about
it early rather than later um uh just
remove the extension we need to play is
a horrible idea I don't agree with that
at all why tell me why why would you
why it's a horrible idea don't do it
um I'm telling you not to do it if you
can do it yourself obviously you can do
whatever you want uh in case you're
wondering yes you can wrap quotes around
your strings if you want to and you
probably should so let's go ahead and do
that
um uh let's see it may clash with the
future Reserve word um so there we go
and we're going to run that SL hello
hello world all right
uh including Windows method of using
file s yeah well
that's not the unix's way if you're
going to use Windows file extensions
then yeah yeah so um here you go you got
the so you got op home Homebrew bin bash
and that's where bash lives that's where
the bash executable program Liv we
talked about what interpreters are and
all of that so bash is a binary program
that runs right in memory of the
computer and it interprets the commands
to follow into signals I mean into
system calls and stuff that are talking
directly to the computer for you that's
why it's called an interpreter um so
bash is a compiled language and Echo
hello world is a statement that gets
parsed and then put into those
instructions that get sent to the
computer um as long as you're on the
same computer this is safer it's always
safer to say this is where my batch is
use this one but if but as you can tell
you know if I'm on a a Linux machine it
doesn't have home brew on it right it
would have user bin back
and no matter how much you may want
everything to live in the same place
very frequently it doesn't so if that if
you're using something that doesn't
require a high level of security and
you're using your own machine for this
then you can get away with another trick
user V EnV bash and that will find bash
wherever it is and run it and then do
the same thing so so that means that
that exact code you know in the GitHub
repo if you download that to your your
Linux machine uh your windows wl2 or
whatever it will still work because it
will find bash wherever it is as long as
it's on the system um in production you
would never want to do that in
production you would always want to
specify the exact path to bash for lots
of performance of security reasons um so
that's the thing um the insecure
argument against the use of that is
because is the same reason we used to
have to define the path up front because
you can eject something that's named
bash in the path ahead of the actual
program and it will run in place of the
other thing so it allows you to have
path injection attacks on a system which
is one level you know less secure than
not having that if if you are explicitly
defining the version of Bash that's
being used you are never subject to that
attack so that's the reason and if you
don't know what that means listen up
because we're now going to talk about
how a path gets resolved if if if they
they don't have to tamper with your path
they have to tamper with stuff that you
have in your path so let's say let's say
a user gets well let's talk about what
path is first okay so the path my
friends is all of the different places
that your programs can live that don't
have to have the explicit path in the
case of we've been doing slash we've
been doing SL high this is an explicit
albeit local path dot means here in this
directory right here and slash means
this directory right here right dot dot
slash would mean the directory above it
right now I could have done this I could
have said uh like where are we I could
have said you know I don't want to but I
I could do this right if I wanted to do
the explicit path I could
say let's do it say SL high and this is
the same thing thing right because for
security reasons that I like I just
mentioned you know anything that is not
in your path cannot be run without being
precisely fully pathed out and that
includes relative path called dot looc
that's why you have to do do local by
the way never ever ever add dot to your
path which we're about to do it is one
of the biggest beginner mistakes ever
made don't do it it's so insecure it's
so dangerous so you always want to force
people to type slash to run things in
the current directory and if you don't
want that then when it's ready put it
someplace that it can be run in one of
these places well how do you set what
those places are okay so the way that
those places get set is in your bash RC
or you can already look at the one
that's already there I have a program
called path this is a very simple
program that that is U it's a very
simple program that we'll get into later
this is actually a really good example
of something called parameter expansion
and what it does is it takes the path
environment variable we already talked
about those it takes the path
environment variable which is this big
long ugly thing and it replaces all the
colons with a line return that's all it
does it's one line it's nice and pretty
and it just helps you see the ones that
come first are the ones that resolve
first so I talked earlier somebody was
questioning the use of user BNB to do a
p path attack if I put the bash binary
if I put if I if I have if I am a
malicious user on the system and I have
access to any of these directories at
all in any way and I can make a binary
that runs there that's named bash that
program will win it will win because
it's not explicitly defined that's why
it's insecure because if if something
else can grab that thing and they want
even know a normal a normal path
injection attack would would be what you
would do with your injection attack is
you would say okay I'm going to make a
program named sh zsh bash all the all
the common things that people use Python
3 python anything that somebody would
think that they're using and if you have
access to their you know to their path
ahead of them then that thing will run
instead of the other thing and you can
have it run and still call the other
thing so you can have it do all kinds of
side effects on because they're running
it they're running it with their
permissions so this is a very very
legitimate hacker Target it's one of the
greatest ways to escalate permissions is
by looking you know you search for the
system for everybody that's using user V
EnV on the system and then you see which
directories these people are using in
their past which you can also identify
and then you put stuff in there that's
that's trojaned in the path and then
then they run it when next time they log
in they run these things with their
escalated permissions perhaps an
administrator and then they this is why
administrators won't run anything with
user VV period because they know better
because if they go on there as Ruder
Studio or something and they actually
get Trojan like this they can actually
get you as an administrator to run
something with elevator permissions that
you normally would not that they would
not run and then you can create you can
create a setu ID binary that has full
permissions as root because they and you
just got at root access that's how it
happens and in fact it's such a
dangerous thing in a multi-user system
that that in the old days we had to
explicitly set the path variable in our
program in this particular case we would
do this we would say path path path
equals
blank so we would do that export path
blank and we would in the old days in
the old this it was so important in a
multi-user we have less concern for this
because there's not as many multiuser
systems but in a multiuser system if
you're writing a system script you would
do this you would do you would do you
know user bin usually user bin path user
bin bash and you would have export path
and you would say nothing can run here
and the thing that's so great about this
is that um required file not found
whoops wait because it can't find bash
right so we could say um
wait is there not a user oh wait it's
bin bash
whoopsie sorry guys that's it's a thing
all right so so this this is now
extremely secure in the old days path
equals a blank or something in the old
days by doing this um they if you try to
do an LS command it will
fail because it's like I don't have no
idea where LS is and so by setting an
explicit path and and this is still a
thing
if you look at the dash scripts in
Debian and some of those scripts right
there some of them do this because it is
so important that some of the stuff gets
run as root and it is so critically
important that this stuff explicitly say
I only want to enable stuff at these
locations and so it will explicitly say
it and by by setting the path like this
you automatically secure your script
from any kind of path injection attack
now you're a beginner you have you may
not have cared about all of that
but I'm telling you right now that this
is the way to do it and and if you want
to be the more Ser if you're writing a
system script then you should do this
but if you're writing a bunch of stuff
for yourself which you know somebody was
giving me crap about this because I
changed and softened my position on this
if I'm writing a bunch of stuff in my
DOT files and it's just going to run and
it's only going to be me on my laptop
and only my laptop then then the
convenience of having user bin ENB uh
which was invented by Ruby people by the
way that was the first people that that
I know of used it uh Pearl people did it
a little bit but they didn't pull get
they didn't really start using it until
the Ruby people started so you can use
your in bash and then that'll that'll
run bash uh as as it's as it's found in
your path um uh it run inside of script
it will not affect any of the commands
running inside of the script all it will
do is force the path force you to
explicitly add to the path all the
things that are being
used okay is by doing that you put that
thing the the fact is if you're a
security person you care about this and
I'm preparing future hat you know black
white gray hat hackers you just need to
know about the path okay you need to
know that it exists that it's a thing if
you want here's two reasons you need to
know it number one you want to own
people you want to own somebody with
root access say hey dude I need I need
some help over here right and then you
go ahead and put that and you do path
injection you can take
over you you can do a path injection you
can take over man I guarantee you I
guarantee if I wanted to social engineer
somebody into root access on a system I
would say I'd get an admin okay I'd get
an admin I'd say come over here I need
some help and then they would I would
get them to suo something for me and I
would inject uh a r Trojan bash into the
path that they didn't even know about
they would run it they would give me
setu id route access to the system and
then I would delete it and they would
know there was no there' be no evidence
of it because there's no there's no
history of what files have been deleted
or on the system you you want to get
root access that's how you do
it that's how you get root access from
an admin you want a social
engineer and you have to know what
you're doing but people have done it
people have done it and you know it's
funny is I mean I'm not telling you to
do this but you'd be surprised you you'd
be surprised how stupid admins are some
of the admins are they they they will
not even they don't even know about this
and so now you do you know about it and
and more importantly you know what path
is okay you know what path
is uh important teic okay so this the
reason I'm going off on this in my
rethinking of this whole entire way I
teach you bash is because I don't want
you to walk away from this thinking this
is a good practice to do in production
okay it's not the only reason this is
even a thing is because bash is in five
different places depending on what
computer you're on and I don't want to
have to screw with it for my files for
my DOT files that's the only reason to
even do it we run fake login on
terminals and wait for people to log in
hell yeah epic yeah you know exactly
what I'm talking about right right so
okay now you guys know okay and I'm not
making Netflix Engineers here I'm making
secure Systems Operations and cyes who
are really really crazy good at what
they do and they are doing it right
they're doing it securely I'm not you
know helping you like bust out a bunch
of stuff and learn through the learn
what the terminal is by learning
neim true story somebody learned neovim
by learning learn what the first time
they ever used a terminal was inside of
neovim that's not what I'm targeting you
for I'm targeting you for Systems
Operations okay so here we go we've got
these two programs are running now you
know what the path is okay so how do we
play around with the path well one of
the things we could do is we could say
if it's in my lab I want to make it run
right so how do we do that well we have
to edit this file there's a file on your
system it's called bash RC right now you
can put it in profile or bash profile or
any of these other places but right now
the first thing we're going to do we
want to stop having to like type. slash
every time so because we trust this
particular directory so we're going to
go add it and we're going to go add it
to the end of it um I already I got lots
of other stuff in here but if let's say
so the way to normally do this and this
is you just have to trust me on this and
make sure you get this right if you
screw this up you want to see me screw
it up do you guys want to see me screw
it
up everybody who's watching right now
has I I guarantee you they let me show
you what happens when you screw it up
okay if if you accidentally put the
wrong path in there you won't be able to
do anything so watch uh make sure I get
an extra terminal here all right so
okay watch this okay so I'm going to
actually I'm going to export export path
equals blank like this
right I can't do anything oh my gosh
everybody's done
this a couple people were saying they've
done this in their lifetime right
everybody's like oh I need to add a new
thing to my path and they accidentally
take over their path and they're like oh
no what have I done and it's even worse
when you do it in your Bachelor C
because now you you can't edit your bash
RC because you don't have B it can't
find LS it can't find anything it your
path is empty it has nothing there's no
commands you can do at all it can't find
anything you just made your shell really
secure you can't do anything so you know
I think you can do built-ins Echo let's
like Echo hello yeah okay you can do it
the the host name thing is because my
PWD my my line is keeps asking for it
it's so secure I can't do anything all
right so how could I do that right well
in this particular case I just start up
a new sh uh but if you really had to do
it you have to use the full path all
right you can use the absolute path yes
so any emergency event that you do this
to your bash RC and you need to edit
your bash RC to fix it the way to do
that is to provide the full path to the
thing H and I don't even think which
works no it doesn't God so so you need
to do like I don't even know where Bim
is I think it's uh and you can't LS to
know where it is is it Ben Vim is it Ben
Vim nope okay user user user Benin
Vim dropping
frames yeah I did drop frames there for
a second I noticed user bin them
yes show me all the things Vim okay
there we go okay so if you had to you
could do user Vin vim and you could you
know open up your Bachelor C file and
fix it right in my case I don't really
have to do this I just have to exit
because I didn't change it right but
just be really careful with this because
as soon as you do this you will do this
wrong usually what people will do is
they'll do something like this they'll
do path colon right and I'm going to
show you a trick because I don't want to
write the whole place that I am I'm
really lazy so I'm going to write PWD
right here and I'm going to do bang bang
two exclamation points bash and that
will send the line to the bash thing and
replace it with its
output okay and we're going to cover
bash completion yeah so so you see what
it did there I didn't want to type it in
my program there's other ways to do that
I I could have done something like this
I could do I think what is it R God I
don't even know the commands but some
people do R and then they do uh
bang um I think PWD yeah that does the
same thing I my I'm just I I like
writing code that writes code so I like
write a little bit of code I'll put a
PWD here and then I'll Transform it
really quickly with bang bang bash enter
you can make that a macro and then I
join it up okay now this is still wrong
though um it's called a filter it's
called a it's called a Vim
filter and what it does is it sends the
current line to the command that you
indicate and then replaces that line or
whatever you selected with the output
that's what it does it's a way to do
math and all kinds of stuff so like if
you want to do scale uh equals 2 uh 2 /
3 you can send that to
BC uh that also works you can do read
yeah you can do RP works too people have
all all kinds of things but this I don't
want to type sometimes I want multiple
lines right and I want to send all those
lines um so so here I go bang bang and
I'm going to send this to BC and it
replace it with its output right um
there's nothing wrong with doing the
read if you want to do that um so but I
I'm like this right for I you know
sometimes I might want to have a few
lines in there and and I'll I'll write a
little program and it'll be two or three
lines long and instead of doing
Exclamation point Exclamation point I'll
do exclamation point right curly bracket
and then it will send the block and
replace the whole block with the output
so I regularly will write code you know
like right here and and then just
replace the code with its own output by
sending it to an interpreter of some
kind and you can send it to all kinds of
interpreters there's all kinds of things
right so and that's how I do that's how
I prefer to do comments I just do
comments that way because it's faster
than visual mode um these these head
these H title lines are all the same
thing so I say hello and I do bang bang
H title and it will replace it with the
title um I could have like H title I
think I think I can but I don't know I
have to I that one's not the point is is
that I have like an ecosystem of filter
commands and I just keep using them that
way so anyway there's a big big problem
here that I have wrong what have I got
wrong here guys
most of the people who kill themselves
when it comes to like path like we just
did this is what they do what's
wrong what's wrong with
it yeah it's missing a dollar and I
guarantee you there's at least two or
three or 10 people watching right now
that have done
this they've forgotten to put the dollar
sign and if you forget to put the dollar
sign you just got rid of all the
directories that have LS and PWD and B
and everything so make sure you don't
forget the dollar sign all right what
we're doing is we're just adding more
stuff onto the end here and um in order
to get your new stuff to be visible you
know here's the moment of truth right
I'm a little scared to do this live
because if I screwed it up it's going to
be very embarrassing you do exact bash
DL and what that does is it replaces
your currently running shell command
with a new one that's also login shell
so that but has the new settings and
that's all that does right so now when I
type my fancy path command you can see
that the one that I added to the end
here has been added to the end okay now
this is really great because now watch
when I do which hello what does which do
put it in your notes people what does
which do which hello will tell you which
hello program would have been
added uh try to add it to the end ofth
then you protect system commands
absolutely yep okay the only time you
wouldn't want to do that by the way is
of course the first thing wins right so
the only time there are some times that
you might want to Shadow an existing
command so um I mean it depends on the
command there's a couple commands that
that I don't find a lot of utility with
and that they have existed forever and
like open I think is one of them and um
another trick is you can put a script
that's going to call an actual binary
someplace El I do this with my links
command I have a links program that I
want to use that runs the same binary
links but it actually you know does it
all of it setup and then runs it so
sometimes you might want to put a
program that takes over another program
up higher in the list but almost you
know the safer thing is to add it to the
end of your list and that way if nothing
else exists then it will it will work um
that's important too because every
single script that you run is going to
use your path everything does by default
that's why it's so important to
explicitly you know Define your path in
highly secure shell scripts because you
don't want them to get path injected so
there you go that's what we're going
we're going on so the thing is cool
about this now is that I can type hello
and hi and I could be anywhere I could
be in my home directory and it works I
could be in the root directory and I can
type hi and it works because it just
finds it it knows where to find it so so
let me do hello and we see that oh hey
look at that it's running a different
one why is it running that one
instead because like I said it looks
like I have a Hello program that is
higher than the other one interesting
right so can you you see let's see which
which high is it using look at
that you found it
first yeah okay so so what it did so
hello is I have two hellos I didn't know
that it's good it's a good example so
you can see that even here's the other
thing even when I'm in the you know my
the whatever what am I
doing lab sample right so even when I'm
in here and the program is right in
front of me it still doesn't run that
program do you see what I'm saying with
security right
so hopefully that's starting to click
because like right here I can unless I
do do SL
hello right which we know is the right
hello it's going to run the other hello
so I do which hello right but high is
the same one so even though I'm typing
hello it's not running the hello that's
right in front of me it's running the
hello that resolves in the path and
that's what Witch is about okay so put
that in your in your in your notes um is
the thing all right so let's keep going
we have we're almost burned up another
hour here so we've got our high and our
low which we already did before and the
first time I taught this a couple couple
days ago I went and I we we went right
down the if then else conditions and
stuff like that but I I want to do this
a different
way uh does export take the bar values
out of the global list and send to
processes is that why it's called export
no what export does is it it makes it it
exports it into the name spaces the
environmental name spaces of everything
under it it exports it into any child
processes whatsoever whether it's b
anary or shell script or anything so you
guys remember Pro process trees right
you remember what processes are about
right so we have all these running
processes on the
system
um uh SP sps3 uh grip uh I mean this is
a pretty big big tree
here yeah so this is all the processes
that are running on the system this is a
huge process tree um and you know all
there all the things that are if you do
top you can see all the running
processes right the pro all the
processes is a running program and you
can send signals to them which is what
the whole control- C thing is about if
you send an interrupt signal to a
process it stops uh it interrupts it and
it can trap it and all that thing so
we'll get into that later that's a Linux
unit thing actually it's a systems thing
it's more of that than it is anything
else it's not a it you kind of need to
know it if you're going to be you know
an operations person but it's it's you
know strictly speaking it's not a part
of computer science uh as much as it is
a part of how operating systems work um
so anyway we've got hello and high let's
look at them we got our hello and we got
our high and okay we actually have a
problem right here because our hello is
that other hello is is getting in the
way so so I'm actually going to go
remove it and I'm going to I'll show you
a trick for this be very careful with
the trick I'm about to show you so I'm
going to delete uh that program I'm not
there I'm nowhere near there but I don't
want to go there I'm too lazy so I want
to remove that file even though I'm not
in that directory so I'm going to do RM
which and I did a back tick there the
back tick is kind of you don't know
about it yet but it's the same as that
I'm going to do that and I'm going to
say remove which hello and now I just
without any confirmation blew that thing
away and so now when I do which hello
it'll resolve to the right one and now
when I run hello it gets it finds the
right one now um it's still hashed to
the other one though so when this
happens this is you have to
rehash is it is it what is it hash do
whatever you can either exact bash DL
which is what I usually do but there's a
command to rehash what it does is Bash
keeps track of all the last locations of
files and we deleted so it can find it
faster and we deleted it and there's a
command for that but I can't remember it
how how do I rehash in bash
after uh removing a binary from path if
you take something out of your path for
for efficiency reason bash does this
it'll um it you have to reash it there
it is is it hashr remove a single
command from the hash okay just hashr
okay so
hashr and now we say which
hello yeah there it is okay so now when
we type hello it'll find it and we're
good to go um I always have to look it
up I I knew it was hash but I couldn't
remember what this thing was so that
that's more than I would normally cover
with a beginner but we were only on
hello and hi you know what variables are
you know what commands are you know how
to make them executable you know how to
safely set up your path now let's move
on to the next thing okay what if I want
to make a program that that you know
also can be used by another program and
this gets kind of interesting okay so
let's do this so what is a
date um so there's the date program
right and um this is a significant
departure from how I used to teach
programming in Python and JavaScript and
stuff because I am teaching it from a
shell perspective and shell is all about
combining in commands that's what it's
for and it's really good at so we have
this program this command that sends the
date and you can actually make the date
really pretty uh in fact I think
um uh yeah I see now so here here's H
this I'm kind of giving away the answer
here but so you see what you can do with
the date you can put all these fancy
things and make it nice and pretty but
the point is is that you can actually
use it someplace else so what we want to
add
to our high program is we want to add
the date you know it's like we want to
say something like it's a beautiful
Monday how about that so let's first of
all look at the date command and like
how could we just get the date to show
the day uh you know it's like so we can
say date Dash uh Mand dat to see what it
is I don't know what it is it's probably
going to be or we can go to my AI yeah I
don't even care watch this how how do I
isolate my date to just the long
English uh
weekday I I could go reading through the
man page or I could just ask my
AI they're the same I have to look it up
no matter what so I don't want to hear
it either way I have to look it up it's
not cheating either way I would be
reading the Man pages just so much that
my AI is much faster I mean I don't want
to go look at look at how far I'd have
to read through this thing I just got
the answer much faster than that okay so
anyway that's there's no shame in doing
that and frankly you're going to need to
do that or you're going to lose a job so
so here we go how do I how do I use this
now right how do I use this how do I use
this really awesome thing so I'm going
to put let's say do we want to is it
high or hello let's do hi hi's got name
in there we just put a shebang in line
in here here because we you know we know
what it is now so let's put a shebang uh
user Ben uhb bash and we'll re reload it
you don't have to do that to get it to
do the thing but it's a good idea to do
that so we could say hi so and so uh
uh uh nice and then we're going to say
date right we want the date so let's say
what the date is right here date plus a
uh uh isn't
um how about that to you or something we
don't want a question yet
so um the about clean code I don't want
to talk about it I we're not talking
about clean code it's a bunch of
just like anything else from
Uncle Bob all right so here we go we're
gonna
say SL high and it says uh okay it says
hi
Rob let go back here and say hey
uh
nice bah blah blah to you right so hi
now I didn't have to do that I could
just do hi now hey Rob nice Monday to
you all right so do you see how you see
what it
did it took another program ran the
program took the output of the program
and put it into a variable that it's
used in the other program that's a very
very unicy thing to do you you make a
bunch of little programs that do what
you want and then you compose them
together in different ways that is the
unix's way that is the Unix way of doing
things um and there's no need for
plugins or anything because you can just
write other executables in whatever
language you want and they are modularly
able to be included into one another
right so like if I wanted to I could say
we can make another program here you see
how that's date I I really like the fact
that that is the um that it's the
weekday you know and I had a hard time
remembering it so what if I did this
what if I made another program here
right so we call it
weekday
weekday and we schod it plus schmod plus
X weekday and I call these I mean you
can keep them small there's no there's
no rule against it and then we can put
that in there right hell I I can let's
make it bash this case I know it's going
to always user B actually in this case I
can just use bsh because I don't need
bash right I don't need bash there's
nothing about this command that needs to
be bash at all so I can just make it
plain old posic Shell and that's simpler
it's faster to run it's safer so now
when I run weekday I get the week date
all
right it's pretty cool right so the
thing that's great about that is now I
can change my other program instead of
it having it be date I can change it to
be
weekday and now I can say hi and it's it
does it okay and um you know it's you
know it's really funny you want to see
something
cool yeah let me show something about
weekday you could you could say say plus
uh um in two weeks
in uh
half a week I think you can do that you
can actually do some weird stuff
yeah no it didn't work anyway there
there's some you can actually use date
to
calculate you know offsets and to come
up with it you can use natural language
it's pretty cool so anyway that's like
the date command and it's just a
oneliner now you're like well God you
know why would you make it like that
then you can have to use it everywhere
right and by the way why would you make
it a script as opposed to you know maybe
in your bash RC function so you there's
another way to do this would be to put
it in your bash orc instead and then you
can always use it but there's a very
serious disadvantage to doing this so if
you do it this way we're going to do it
so if we say weekday okay you you don't
know about functions yet but so let's
learn about how to do it how do I do the
same exact thing in here so there's the
command but how do I make it so that
it's into a command without really being
a command well enter functions okay
these are I call them sub routines
because they're more accurately called
that but so now you can do this you
could say
weekday and now you could you have to do
the thing I mean there's many ways to do
this that and but this is this is the
standard way right and so now I have a
weekday function now the thing you have
to do remember that whole thing about
exporting so you can't use this function
anywhere else but here unless you do an
export so traditionally what we'll do is
we'll do and Export DF weekday this is a
bash only thing this doesn't work in z
shell or posic shell but now that
function is built into the shell now
there are advantages to having a shell
function and there are disadvantages the
most serious disadvantage is that I
can't use this function in a go
program because the go program can't see
this in this this function the only
thing that can use the function is
another shell
program period and also um I mean it can
be could you could actually export it
and it will work if the calling shell
the parent shell of the go program is
you know also bash but if it's not let's
say it's on Powershell or something it
won't work right so there's arguments
against having a function in my case the
only time to have a function inside of
your bash RC is when you really want it
to make a difference and I have one
called clone in here that actually
changes what directory you're running in
and that's one of the only
reasons you should ever have a shell uh
A bash RC function in my opinion because
the the criteria should be is it going
to change my state and state is your
current working directory you cannot
write a program that will change your
working
directory in a in a script you can't do
it because the changing into that
directory is a property of the child
process that's running and it's now in
there but as soon as that process gets
dies and goes away all of the state of
the collar comes back and so you pop
back up to your you don't really pop
back up you never we're down below and
then you come back up right and there's
no way it's impossible for you to change
and have it keep you in another
directory unless that was executed in
the exact running shell that you're in
right now this is really common error
beginners make all the time so they they
think that can like you know do the
thing like that you can't so but if so
if you want to the bottom line is this
if you want to change anything about
your currently running shell including
your current working directory it has to
be in a function or an alias all right
and it can't be in a separate script
however if you want to write code that
can be Rewritten in go or Rewritten as a
multicol binary or Rewritten in Pearl or
Rewritten in C then you should start
even if it's only one line you should
start out with you know these tiny
executable scripts or whatever because
those can be replaced and they will work
anywhere they will work anywhere they'll
work in anything that ever calls it so
and then that that gives you a lot of
functionality later on this is going to
become much more relevant later when we
talk about using the Bonsai commandry
Branch Builder which actually allows you
to make a single binary that's got
hundreds of little tiny programs in them
that are all what's called a multical
binary so they TR as a single binary
even though they all look like they're
independent commands we're going to get
to that later so right now what we have
is the ability to run weekday weekday is
a is a thing and by the way that's
that's where the word type comes in so
when you want to see so the only thing
witch shows you the only the only thing
wit shows you is um if it's in your path
or not right which hello which I don't
know so which which uh bo so you know it
doesn't show you thing but uh so how
about this which clone there's no such
thing as clone like I know there's a
clone command so you use type for that
type will show you that the Clone is a
function type type will also show you
hello is a thing and where it's at so
that's the difference between which and
type uh there's one other thing it's
called command-v which is also
specifically for executables when you
want to know the exact path uh this will
not work if it on a function so it'll
give you the which is you know kind of
wrong so a lot of people say to use that
I don't I I I I use witch almost
universally uh you're learning so many
things I hope you're learning things
good so the next thing here is we got
okay so we're we're we've got a couple
minutes left on this one let's catch
back up we're in one hour we've caught
them back caught back up to what we were
doing before in the in the earlier days
I put all these different things into
into function and I did the whole
language thing right the whole grading
thing so but let's we we concluded the
last hour by putting a random color into
a uh into a function but let's do the
same thing but this time let's use one
of let's let's keep him into the Unix
way one tiny program that does something
really well and integrates with other
things that is literally the Unix
philosophy I'm going to ask her what is
the Unix philosophy
right it's not a bunch of functions the
Unos is a set of guiding principles by
Ken Thompson Dennis Richie and Doug K
Ken Thompson by the way one of the
primary contributors to the go
programming language along with Rob Pike
uh do one thing well write programs that
do one thing well rather than large
monolithic programs a lot of people
would say that in
2024 this this still is doable get has
is what's called a monolith there are
lots of monoliths in 2024 but their
first verb their first action is is is
kind of in compliance with us right um
so you you could you could argue pretty
strongly that in modern times now that
we have memory and everything that this
do one thing well has come to include
like sort of an umbrella program like
get or GitHub command line or you know
anything you can make with Bonsai so
that you have do one thing well but the
first verb is like they do one thing
well composed programs make programs
that when you add them together in all
the ways that we just did you get a
larger program and then you focus on one
thing that that works really well even
if it's only one line and then another
thing use text as a universal interface
that's another common thing make sure
that they they work together and that
this is very much the Unix philosophy um
so this is why so much so many things
are in text because of this so let's we
already did it we got you know weekday I
mean weekday is like nice and simple
it's like one little command but you
know we don't have to go look it up
every time now we can use that as as if
it were you know reusable anywhere
because it's in our path so let's keep
let's let's keep going with this idea we
what what if we were to make one that
would show us the color so I have a a
program called uh term colors that just
dumps out the term colors right well
what if we could make a command that
would actually send a random color uh
command all right what if we did that so
we already wrote the code for this so
let's write it again all this time let's
write it as a separate command instead
of as a function so we're going to make
a new program so touch uh Rand color
name it wherever you want dashes in in
names is totally fine uh underscores in
names is usually not fine um dashes are
regularly used all over the place um you
can just do Rand color if you want I I
kind of like the dash in this one um you
know I enter into evidence every single
SSH command that's ever been
made so you know whatever so Rand let's
do Rand color I have a lot of Rands I I
use Rand as a prepix for lots of
different things so let's make one so
Rand color uh Schmo what is Schmo type
Schmo you guys want a Schmo do you want
a Schmo let's add a Schmo okay so let's
add an alias really quick do bash orc
I'm going to show you how to add it and
I already have one but let's show you
how to add it bash ah bash RC we're
going to add a Schmo
Alias uh Schmo
equals uh
schmod plus X okay save that boom you
got your a that's how you get your Alias
from then on exit bash DL restart you
know your shell and then you've got it
so now now you can instead of having to
type that because it's so hard to type
right I mean I type it a lot I have
another I have another command is called
New X which uh automatically makes a new
command in the right place and and then
it it puts the user BV bash at the
beginning and schmoes it and then opens
up my editor and starts editing on it
yeah you can write your own this just
the beginning my friends just the
beginning so so you're going to have a
lot of fun stuff this is ridiculously
addicting by the way doing all this fun
stuff all right so there's no user bemv
wouldn't it be nice if that was
automatically
created yeah yeah now I could make a
macro a million things you could do here
right but I'm not I'm just going to do
user bin EnV bash now let me show you
how uh let me show you how to get cus
knows how addicting this is so
um uh okay so you see how my file type
down at the bottom here says None all
right so there are a couple ways to get
this to reload the file type but let me
show you one that you can just do so you
do you do colon right and then you do um
ft is it set ft ft is stands for file
type and then you change it say Ty pype
equals bash there's probably a faster
way to do that but that's one of the
ways I know is that slower or faster
than just closing it and reopening it
you decide but that's now it knows what
I'm writing right so let's go ahead and
write this what what is our bash command
going to do it's going to print a random
color so let's start by by dumping the
colors in here and you don't have them
so you're going to have to go look them
up um but you see how I have posix and
then I also have bash all right so we're
going to stick with the bash
ones and uh we actually don't need all
the different colors in fact
um we could do a macro here
actually yeah should we attempt a
macro I I don't put underscores in my
Bash ever I put I put dashes unless it's
a variable if it's a variable then I'll
put underscore yeah anything that's
running I use dashes that's pretty
conventional so I was going to do a
macro here I'm not a macro master I
don't use them very much um but I could
this could be really solid macro
opportunity so let's go ahead and start
a macro with uh what is it at no it's Q
right it's Q I think I don't even do
macros I I am not a master of macros
because macros don't work everywhere
that's why I don't know them very well
is it what how do I start a macr someone
help me is it is it is it Q or is it
um at is how you repeat the
macro you know
what you know what I don't need to do
that I don't need to do it you know why
because I'm going to use Pearl instead
so there I'm going to do my
way yep I'm going to do
per Dash any
actually actually we could almost do
this just with a straight up command
without that Pearl even yep we could say
I want to
replace everything up
until the equal sign if I want to delete
it it's easy that's
easy delete it is easy
so yeah anyway I I'm not fast at this
stuff I I tend to think in terms of
filters so let's I'm trying to think in
I'm trying to go out of my comfort zone
and do stuff in here that's doing this
thing so if we do this if we say s dot
and we say
everything up to the uh the equal
sign oops see you can't do it because
it's not a regular expression this is
one of my biggest annoyances this is why
I hate I hate basic regular
Expressions you can't use a plus there
watch watch s
dot which means any character and then I
say plus it doesn't do it plus is a
pearl
thing plus is a pearl
thing okay I have to escape a plus
because I'm using extended regular
Expressions I know I'm going to do
capture groups next but why backs slash
plus Pearl doesn't do that this is why I
don't like using the regular Expressions
that are not
Pearl you know what I mean um what is I
don't even know what that is
so yeah um you know the this this works
generally speaking and then you put an
equal sign right and then okay so that's
kind of okay but now I'm going to do
capture group and I'm going to put the
capture group around
here and then I say okay so now it's got
a capture group and I want to say I want
to dump the capture group at the end so
then I want to say uh I want to put a
hashtag in there
uh where's my hashtag okay here we go
and then space and then the capture
group one comma G no just one enter nope
it didn't do it capture goups didn't
work pattern not found because stupid
regex's yeah I hate regex's in this
language they suck they's so much worse
than Pearl this is why I use Pearl for
everything all right so there you go
um all right so that sort of did it but
I had to escape everything I hated that
I hate that um okay we we put the escape
sequence in the wrong place so let's do
that let's
say uh okay so we need to have it we
have to have it replace it
with um well we have to have this other
part too right so we have to have the
second capture part god I I hate these
regular Expressions these are so
bad they're so freaking ugly all right
so then we're going to replace it with
the second capture
group okay and then a a thing and then
we're going to put uh the
back1 and that's that shows me what I
want now the thing that is nice about
neim and this is a neim thing is that
neim shows you the transformation while
you're doing it so you get kind of a
sense of what's Happening um and you
know that's all well and good right so
that did what I wanted and I didn't have
to do a macro um so I still think that's
better but you could do the same thing
with a pearl a pearl command line filter
let me show you what I mean by that if I
was going to do the same thing with a
pearl command line filter I would do
that I would do thing I'd send it to
Pearl - NE and then I would say
um uh let's see so
we could either if we put a p in there
then okay so we do a we do a we wrap it
up all right so we're going to do a
replacement and we say uh I'm going to
try this and it's not going to show me
while I'm doing it because it's a filter
so I'm going to do actual regx is that
you know the God intended which is Pearl
Pearl are the world's best regular
expressions and um I can do plus here
actually this one you can say uh I think
we could do that and that would say
don't get too greedy
I because plus is going to include the
colon unless it's too greedy so I have
to tell it not to be
greedy either that I could just say this
I could say uh not uh equal sign plus um
which is you know they're kind of both
the same so that would be a thing and
then over here we say that plus plus
equals
and um so then we
say uh so that that's how we do that
then we did
print um oh actually we could use an F
in here too so you could say you could
say we just want to print
um uh is it
dollar I'm wondering if we'd have to
do I'm trying to think here I've been
I've been wanting to get
better yeah I
think yeah I'm trying to trying to
remember is it um
it's not
F what is it is it
underscore God I've lost my Pearl so
much I wrote it so much but that's a
better regular
expression macro is not
easier no it's not I mean a macro a
macro is easier if you want okay so
let's do a macro for those people who
say they want to do a
macro all right so let's do
macros let's try a
macro how do I start a macro I know I
know
people do crazy macros all the time the
okay the problem with macros is is that
you only have so many of them so don't
get a if you're as soon as you start
saving multiple macros it's probably
time to put into a script but I agree I
need to get better with macros so I
can't remember how to start a macro
though it's like is it QQ it's QQ for
macro okay so now we go so now it's
recording everything I do so let's do
this let's say I want to
uh okay so I want to delete up
to uh the equal sign DT equals
enter and then uh and then I'm going to
paste it onto the end so contrl a and
then escape and
P and then um go back to the be
actually let me undo that and we can
say um a I'm sorry
there and now we can
do uh P okay and then we can get rid of
the thing at the beginning so we can go
to the beginning and then and then X
oops and then X and then uh and now that
does the transformation and now we can
save the macro which is Q again
right isn't it Q
again is it Q I think it's
Q yeah I think you have to do like q and
then with the with the letter is after
that and and Q by default is the macro
so you go down here and then to get the
macro you do was it
a I can't remember is it AQ or is it
it's AQ
right I think I can't remember I think
it's Q whatever back at the beginning of
the next line so you can chain them
right so right or you could do this you
could
say Q wait
which one is the I can't remember which
one it
is I don't I don't do macros I'm telling
you I don't I never have I never needed
them and my pearls gotten Rusty because
I've gotten so fast with just regular
stuff so I a big spammer of things is it
add Q add Q because Q is a default right
so add
Q yeah it didn't quite do that one yeah
this is my problem with macros I do
think it's worth getting good with them
but I'm clearly not let I'm going to try
it I'm GNA try it again all right so QQ
let's say all right
um let's say delete delete slash
equals
enter uh and then X and then uh
capital a space and then Escape and then
P oops and it did the last restored
thing yeah so X counts as lead thing I
thought maybe it didn't yeah I hate
macros man I hate him I always have
hated him but that that doesn't mean I'm
a master edit or whatever I I like Pearl
Transformations this what I'm used to
doing and I I'm a big filters fan
because once you do a macro then it's
gone
forever so
I don't like
that yeah there's like a good macro
let's try that so
QQ QQ what are you doing zero
right okay so that goes to the beginning
of the line and then we delete up to uh
you're doing delete the word but that's
that's not going to get rid of
the yeah I mean the is is cool I mean
that deletes one word but then you have
to add it to the
end um what what is the what are you
doing with the with the
[Music]
um what are you doing with the double
quotes I don't know if you need it or
not you definitely don't need as a
beginner which I know we're totally off
on this
video Z secure Z inste of
oh okay yeah I don't I don't know if I
like
that yeah
so I don't know what your I don't I
don't know what your double quot is
for but that's that's not a thing for me
so anyway
so uh QQ qq0 let's see
qq0 um so I would
normally I I thought maybe you were
going to uh to the zero
position yeah so we're GNA do D I mean
diw it will delete the word that's
fine but then we need to add it to the
end so capital A to go to the
end and then uh space uh pound sign P
wait Escape P okay and then we need to
go to the beginning again so that's zero
and then
delete and then
um uh I guess we could go down to the
bottom of the next line so we go down to
the bottom of the next line and
then um Q again all right so now I can
do uh is it at
zero at zero yeah at zero and then after
you do the first one then you can just
do dot to repeat the last macro so dot
whoops apparently
not can you not do that so add at does
the last macro Right add at does the
last macro add at add at add at add at
add at add at okay so there we
go we on the last macro it tell it to
delete x uh double quote tells it to
delete X into the underscore register
you want to put it into a register and
then paste it into the into the black
hole
register does that does that work in
only Bim again people one of the reasons
I don't do macros is because they're I
know pretty sure they're the kind of
macros that people are using right here
are not bi compatible that's why I never
learned them because they I'm pretty
sure they
aism and that's I'm almost positive
that's why I didn't I didn't learn them
I I actually had to ask Chloe about this
are Vim macros compatible
with
VI and there's a lot of reasons like da
diw C dap ciw all these things that I
never learned in Bim because I learned
VI and I use them all the time now so
I'm always open to things short answer
basic B macros might work in traditional
VI but anything that relies on Bim
special features for commands play
including buffers by the way like the
black hole will not work your further
recorded macro stat from classic bi
commands less likely to be compatible
you know know what is compatible filters
they work no matter what everywhere so
that's why I tend to be filter a filter
for preference okay anyway that was a
big rabbit hole sorry but you know if
you want to do that go ahead uh I don't
want to paste equals which is why I
black told it okay gotcha um all right
so let's do this how do we put that into
a function now so we're going to put
this into an array which you already did
so we'll put it in we actually don't
need a function here but we could put
one if we want wanted right so if you
wanted to you could just declare all
these but to tell you the truth we
really don't need to but we do need to
put them into a list okay so let's say
colors equals and we're putting them
into a list otherwise known as an array
I'm using the word list because I like
the python terms for these things
dictionary and list even though you know
there's there's problems with it course
appears unus okay so now we're going to
do the random you already know about
this right we already did this Echo
dollar random dollar random is
guaranteed to have a number between 0
and 2 to 17th minus 1 um no 2 to the
16th minus one is that right 32
whatever um anyway it's
random but if you if you if you Echo it
um if you Echo uh random and you want to
take you want to do some math on
it then you can actually take the
modulus of of it uh if you only have
eight things and it'll give you the
eight but in order to do math you need
to do this and that does math on the
thing integer math by the way there's no
such thing as decimal math in both posix
shell and Bash it does exist in Kell but
it's a huge mistake don't do it um
because people will expect it to not and
you should be using BC for that so we're
going to do a whole thing on math but
for right now we're just when we do for
Loops we're going to do a whole thing on
math so for right now for the math we're
going to have this we're going to say uh
we got
random uh modulus 8 which again divides
it by eight and so whatever the
remainder is is what's left over which
gives us a number between zero and seven
inclusively so now we have that thing so
Echo we can just run it so Rand color
Rand
color is two one I mean hell we could
even make a program that is
just a oneliner that's a random number
between one and
eight right we could do that but we
don't want that so we want to actually
look it up so we're going to say colors
and we're going to look up that index
between zero and and uh eight and0 and
seven inclusively and um okay we can't
we can't use Echo we have to use printf
the reason for that is because Echo does
not do escapes so and prf does not like
um things that are I don't I don't this
is really stupid I really wish it would
do that you could have done just Echo
Das e but that's not compatible across
the board neither is random quite
frankly so let's stick with echo on this
case Echo Das e will do the Escape for
you and it'll shut up because because
there's no random on a system that
doesn't that doesn't have echod e so we
might as well use echod Dashi um print
does always does the escapes so so
that's they're both equivalent now you
get a random color it's like well it's
not doing anything Mr Rob it actually is
um so yeah and what it's doing is it's
taking uh you know a thing
so and it's printing it so we can say
Echo Rand color
something and then it will do it it'll
return it every different color
different random color every time um
what if we made it so it took in a
string or something we want to have it
take the thing in right so let's do that
so instead of having it just do this
let's have it read in the string so
let's say Echo the dollar um we we want
to take the things that came in and um
there's a couple ways of doing this that
well let's just use dollar one because
that that'll be the first word that was
passed in okay and then we can say Echo
go and we can actually do a reset so
let's put reset as its own thing uh
reset
equals this
oops it reset is its own thing and so
equals reset
here and obviously we can put all that
on a single line if we want that's also
fine um I think we need ay on this
one oh
whoops reset
I think we might have an avad dashy in
there yeah so now now we can do this we
can do Echo something wait Rand color
something and it's whatever we send it
it does it now it it's kind of lame
though right because it's putting this
extra line there do we really want that
probably not
so uh watch this stream later after I
get back okay so let's go back here and
we're going to say and let's actually go
back to print F instead because we got
lots of stuff we put in there so let's
do that let's just say print F kind of
easier to keep track of and we'll say
you know the beginning part s and the
ending part s and then we have the
middle part s so then we can have the
color and then we can have you know
dollar one which is the argument that
was the single word that was passed in
and then we have the uh reset so and I I
didn't have to to make these variables
it could have made them direct right so
now when we run it we run something now
you see how it didn't put a line return
in there and that's fine right so um
let's actually go ahead and add a line
return a line return is a back sln I
mean it's not a line return it's a a
line feed strictly speaking but
effectively a line return um I did it
wrong what did I do
wrong
oh stupid
I put it in the the the colors thing and
not the all right so there we go all
right and watch this you can just do
watch oh damn it didn't didn't didn't
colorize it that's too bad you see the
numbers changing though see it's 35 and
32 and whatever that's interesting it's
like it's not escaping the colors when
you run watch watch just runs a thing at
a standard loop it's like every n
seconds it's like putting a for Loop
you know it's exactly the same thing as
that but we're going to do that later
all right so that's enough for today um
you know you want to do the Rand color
as a separate
program uh hello and then whatever you
have in there will be uh a a color now
what if you want to say hello there what
will it do it's only going to print out
that okay so how do we have it group the
whole thing together the first thing we
do is we can put quotes around the whole
thing now it sees the whole thing okay
and that's dollar one now I'm going to
show you a trick though really quick and
that is something called the
dollar uh uh instead of having this
we're going to do Splat and what that
does is that takes all of the arguments
together and jams them into each other
combines them all together so so if you
do that then you can say this instead of
saying hello there it'll still work but
you can also do hello there and you
go and you know you it'll you know it's
a little bit more forgiving it it you
know it's it's not perfect but it is a
way to get rid of having to type quotes
and who wants to type quotes when you're
doing stuff like this so um you know
that's that's that's a way to do it so
so now you can say you got weekday you
got random color there um you could say
we could go back to hello we could add
it there you can say hello world we can
say we go back to hi uh and you can
change you could say you can make the
name automatically a color watch let's
make the name a color all right so let's
say Rand color uh name now that's going
to blow up because why because we don't
want to have shell injection so you put
quotes around it and now we do this we
say um now we can say what is it hi hi
hi Rob nice to meet you hi it's like
different color every time okay
and we're kind of learning how to
compose together a bunch of commands we
have already learned how to do functions
but sometimes it's better to just make
them into individual commands and that's
why I wanted to redo this video um it is
an hour and a half long uh we did go
down quite the rabbit hole with macros I
apologize for that I am not good with
Vim uh to the degree that other people
are but my skills with them are more
Universal they usually apply to VI and
different things that you're going to be
on as opposed to only the neam system
you're working on today so I should
probably learn macros better honestly
but you know what everybody else should
learn filters better because they don't
know them and they sure as hell
shouldn't be learning stupid essential
basic regular Expressions which
are they're just horrible they're
horrible and they're not that same way
and using everything else so so that's
the thing I'm going to stop this video
right now um I am going to make another
video and we're going to return and
we're going to do four loops on bash I
really want to get to the point where
bash is done so everything in your bash
RC is done and I'm kind of motivated to
finish that today uh while I wait for my
wife to come home so I'm going to end
that video now and we'll start another
one in just a second